<chapter id="first-steps">
	<title>Primeiros Passos <!--First Steps--></title>
	
	<section id="first-steps-intro">
		<title>Introdução<!--Introduction--></title>
		<para>
		Veremos agoras como executar um programa "Hello World" tradicional em Python. Isto vai ensiná-lo como escrever, salvar e executar programas em Python.
                <!--
		We will now see how to run a traditional 'Hello World' program in Python. This will
		teach you how to write, save and run Python programs.
		-->
		</para>
		<para>
		Existem duas maneiras de usar Python para executar seu prorgama - usando o prompt interativo do interpretador ou usando um arquivo fonte. Veremos como usar os dois métodos.
                <!--
		There are two ways of using Python to run your program - using the interactive
		interpreter prompt or using a source file. We will now see how to use both the methods.
		-->
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="interpreter-prompt">
		<title>Usando o prompt do interpretador<!--Using the interpreter prompt--></title>
		<para>
                
		Inicie o interpretador na linha de comando, digitando <command>python</command> no prompt de comando do shell. Agora digite <literal>print 'Hello World'</literal> seguido da tecla <keycap>Enter</keycap>. Você verá as palavras <computeroutput>Hello World</computeroutput> como saída.

		<!--Start the intepreter on the command line by entering <command>python</command> at the
		shell prompt. Now enter <literal>print 'Hello World'</literal> followed by the
		<keycap>Enter</keycap> key. You should see the words
		<computeroutput>Hello World</computeroutput> as output.-->
		
		</para>
		<para>
		Usuários de Windows podem executar o interpretador na linha de comando modificando a variável <envar>PATH</envar> para incluir o caminho da instalação do Python. Como alternativa, é possível usar o programa <acronym>IDLE</acronym> . IDLE é a sigla para Integrated DeveLopment Environment. Clique em <guimenu>Iniciar</guimenu> -> <guisubmenu>Programas</guisubmenu> -> <guisubmenu>Python 2.3</guisubmenu> -> <guisubmenu>IDLE (Python GUI)</guisubmenu>. Usuários de Linux também podem usar o IDLE.

		<!--For Windows users, you can run the interpreter in the command line if you have set
		the <envar>PATH</envar> variable appropriately. Alternatively, you can use the
		<acronym>IDLE</acronym> program. IDLE is short for Integrated DeveLopment Environment.
		Click on <guimenu>Start</guimenu> -> <guisubmenu>Programs</guisubmenu> ->
		<guisubmenu>Python 2.3</guisubmenu> -> <guisubmenu>IDLE (Python GUI)</guisubmenu>.
		Linux users can use IDLE too.
		-->
		</para>
		<para>
		Perceba que o sinais de <![CDATA[>>>]]> são o prompt de entrada de comandos do Python.
                <!--
		Note that the <![CDATA[>>>]]> signs are the prompt for entering Python statements.
		-->
		</para>
		<example>
			<title>Usando o prompt do interpretador <!--Using the python interpreter prompt--></title>
			<screen>
			<![CDATA[
$ python
Python 2.3.4 (#1, Oct 26 2004, 16:42:40)
[GCC 3.4.2 20041017 (Red Hat 3.4.2-6.fc3)] on linux2
Type "help", "copyright", "credits" or "license" for more information.
>>> print 'hello world'
hello world
>>>
			]]>
			</screen>
		</example>
		<para>
		Note que Python exibe a saída da linha imediatamente. O que você acabou de digitar é um único <emphasis>comando</emphasis> do Python. Usamos <literal>print</literal> para (previsivelmente) imprimir qualquer valor que seja fornecido. Neste caso, estamos fornecendo o texto <literal>Hello World</literal>, que é logo exibido na tela.
                <!--
		Notice that Python gives you the output of the line immediately! What you just entered
		is a single Python <emphasis>statement</emphasis>. We use <literal>print</literal>
		to (unsurprisingly) print any value that you supply to it. Here, we are supplying the
		text <literal>Hello World</literal> and this is promptly printed to the screen.
		-->
		</para>
		<important>
			<title>Como sair do prompt do Python<!--How to quit the Python prompt--></title>
			<para>
			Para sair do prompt, pressione <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>d</keycap></keycombo> se estiver usando o IDLE ou o shell do Linux/BSD. No caso do prompt de comando do Windows, pressione <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>z</keycap></keycombo> seguido de <keycap>Enter</keycap>.

                        <!--
			To exit the prompt, press
			<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>d</keycap></keycombo>
			if you are using IDLE or are using a Linux/BSD shell. In case of the Windows
			command prompt, press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>z</keycap></keycombo>
			followed by <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
			-->
			</para>
		</important>
	</section>
	<section id="choosing-an-editor">
		<title>Escolhendo um Editor<!--Choosing an Editor--></title>
		<para>
		Antes de começarmos a escrever programas Python em arquivos-fonte, precisaremos de um editor. A escolha de um editor é decisiva. Você deve escolher um editor como se fosse escolher um carro para comprar. Um bom editor vai ajudá-lo a escrever programas em Python de forma fácil, fazendo sua viagem mais confortável, e a alcaçar seu destino (atingir seu objetivo) de maneira mais rápida e segura.
                
                <!--
		Before we move on to writing Python programs in source files, we need an editor
		to write the source files. The choice of an editor is crucial indeed.  You have
		to choose an editor as you would choose a car you would buy. A good editor will
		help you write Python programs easily, making your journey more comfortable and
		helps you reach your destination (achieve your goal) in a much faster and safer
		way.
		-->
		</para>
		<para>
		
                Um dos requisitos básicos de um um editor é o recurso de <emphasis role="bold">realce de sintaxe</emphasis>, no qual todas as diferentes partes do seu código são colorizadas de modo que se possa <emphasis>ver</emphasis> o programa e visualizar sua execução.

                <!--
		One of the very basic requirements is <emphasis role="bold">syntax
		highlighting</emphasis> where all the different parts of your Python program are
		colorized so that you can <emphasis>see</emphasis> your program and visualize its
		running.
		-->
		</para>
		<para>
		
                Se você está usando Window, sugiro que use o IDLE. O IDLE possui recursos de realce de sintaxe e muitos outros, tais como permitir que você execute seus programa a partir do próprio IDLE, entre outros. Um lembrete especial: <emphasis role="bold">não use o Notepad (Bloco de Notas)</emphasis>. É uma escolha ruim, pois não possui realce de sintaxe e não suporta indentação de texto, o que é muito importante no nosso caso, como veremos mais adiante. Bons editores como o IDLE (e também o VIM) vão ajudá-lo automaticamente com essa tarefa.

                <!--
		If you are using Windows, then I suggest that you use IDLE. IDLE does syntax highlighting
		and a lot more such as allowing you to run your programs within IDLE among other things.
		A special note: <emphasis role="bold">don't use Notepad</emphasis> - it is a bad choice
		because it does not do syntax highlighting and also importantly it does not support
		indentation of the text which is very important in our case as we will see later. Good
		editors such as IDLE (and also VIM) will automatically help you do this.
		-->
		</para>
		<para>
	
                Se você usa Linux/BSD, então tem vários editores que pode escolher. Se você é um programador experiente, então já deve estar usando o <application>VIM </application> ou o <application>Emacs</application>. Desnecessário dizer que estes são dois dos mais poderosos editores e você terá benefícios ao usá-los para editar seus programas. Pessoalmente, uso o <application>VIM</application> para a maioria dos meus programas. Se você é um iniciante, então pode usar o <application>Kate</application>, que é um dos meus favoritos. Caso tenha vontade de dispender algum tempo aprendendo VIM ou Emacs, recomendo fortemente que aprenda ambos. Certamente será de grande utilidade a longo prazo.

                <!--
		If you are using Linux/FreeBSD, then you have a lot of choices for an editor. If you are
		an experienced programmer, then you must be already using <application>VIM</application>
		or <application>Emacs</application>. Needless to say, these are two of the most powerful
		editors and you will be benefitted by using them to write your Python programs. I
		personally use <application>VIM</application> for most of my programs. If you are a
		beginner programmer, then you can use <application>Kate</application> which is one of my
		favorites. In case you are willing to take the time to learn VIM or Emacs, then I highly
		recommend that you do learn to use either of them as it will be very useful for you in
		the long run.
                -->
		
		</para>
		<para>
		 
		If you still want to explore other choices of an editor, see the comprehensive
		<ulink url="http://www.python.org/cgi-bin/moinmoin/PythonEditors">list of Python
		editors</ulink> and make your choice. You can also choose an
		<acronym>IDE</acronym> (Integrated Development Environment) for Python. See the
		comprehensive <ulink
		url="http://www.python.org/cgi-bin/moinmoin/IntegratedDevelopmentEnvironments"
		>list of IDEs that support Python</ulink> for more details. Once you start writing
		large Python programs, IDEs can be very useful indeed.
		
		</para>
		<para>
		
		I repeat once again, please choose a proper editor - it can make writing Python
		programs more fun and easy.
		
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="source-file">
		<title>Using a Source File</title>
		
		<para>
		
		Now let's get back to programming. There is a tradition that whenever you learn a new
		programming language, the first program that you write and run is the 'Hello World'
		program - all it does is just say 'Hello World' when you run it. As Simon Cozens
		<footnote>
			<para>
			one of the leading Perl6/Parrot hackers and the author of the amazing
			'Beginning Perl' book
			</para>
		</footnote>
		puts it, it is the 'traditional incantation to the programming gods to help you learn
		the language better' :) .
		
		</para>
		<para>
		
		Start your choice of editor, enter the following program and save it as
		<filename>helloworld.py</filename>
		
		</para>
		<example>
			<title>Using a Source File</title>
			<programlisting>
			<![CDATA[
#!/usr/bin/python
# Filename : helloworld.py
print 'Hello World'
			]]>
			</programlisting>
			<para>
				(Source file: <ulink url="code/helloworld.py">code/helloworld.py</ulink>)
			</para>
		</example>
		<para>
		
		Run this program by opening a shell (Linux terminal or DOS prompt) and entering the
		command <command>python <replaceable>helloworld.py</replaceable></command>. If you
		are using IDLE, use the menu <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> ->
		<guimenuitem>Run Script</guimenuitem> or the keyboard shortcut
		<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F5</keycap></keycombo>. The output is as shown
		below.
		
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Output</title>
			<screen>
			<![CDATA[
$ python helloworld.py
Hello World
			]]>
			</screen>
		</section>
		<para>
		
		If you got the output as shown above, congratulations! - you have successfully run your
		first Python program.
		
		</para>
		<para>
		
		In case you got an error, please type the above program <emphasis>exactly</emphasis> as
		shown and above and run the program again. Note that Python is case-sensitive i.e.
		<literal>print</literal> is not the same as <literal>Print</literal> - note the
		lowercase <literal>p</literal> in the former and the uppercase <literal>P</literal> in
		the latter. Also, ensure there are no spaces or tabs before the first character in each
		line - we will see why this is important later.
		
		</para>
		
		<section>
			<title>How It Works</title>
			<para>
			
			Let us consider the first two lines of the program. These are called
			<emphasis>comments</emphasis> - anything to the right of the <literal>#</literal>
			symbol is a comment and is mainly useful as notes for the reader of the program.
			
			</para>
			<para>
			
			Python does not use comments except for the special case of the first line here.
			It is called the <emphasis>shebang line</emphasis> - whenever the first two
			characters of the source file are <literal>#!</literal> followed by the location
			of a program, this tells your Linux/Unix system that this program should be run
			with this interpreter when you <emphasis>execute</emphasis> the program. This is
			explained in detail in the <link linkend="executable-python-programs"
			>next section</link>. Note that you can always run the program on any platform by
			specifying the interpreter directly on the command line such as the command
			<command>python <replaceable>helloworld.py</replaceable></command> .
			
			</para>
			<important>
				<para>
				
				Use comments sensibly in your program to explain some important details
				of your program - this is useful for readers of your program so that they
				can easily understand what the program is doing. Remember, that person
				can be yourself after six months!
				
				</para>
			</important>
			
			<para>
			
			The comments are followed by a Python <emphasis>statement</emphasis> - this just
			prints the text <literal>'Hello World'</literal>. The <literal>print</literal>
			is actually an operator and <literal>'Hello World'</literal> is referred to as a
			string - don't worry, we will explore these terminologies in detail later.
			
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="executable-python-programs">
		<title>Executable Python programs</title>
		<para>
		
		This applies only to Linux/Unix users but Windows users might be curious as well
		about the first line of the program. First, we have to give the program executable
		permission using the <command>chmod</command> command then <emphasis>run</emphasis>
		the source program.
		
		</para>
		<screen>
		<![CDATA[
$ chmod a+x helloworld.py
$ ./helloworld.py
Hello World
		]]>
		</screen>
		<para>
		
		The chmod command is used here to <emphasis>ch</emphasis>ange the
		<emphasis>mod</emphasis>e of the file by giving e<emphasis>x</emphasis>ecute
		permission to <emphasis>a</emphasis>ll users of the system. Then, we execute the
		program directly by specifying the location of the source file. We use the
		<literal>./</literal> to indicate that the program is located in the current
		directory.
		
		</para>
		<para>
		
		To make things more fun, you can rename the file to just <filename>helloworld</filename>
		and run it as <command>./helloworld</command> and it will still work since the system
		knows that it has to run the program using the interpreter whose location is specified
		in the first line in the source file.
		
		</para>
		<para>
		
		You are now able to run the program as long as you know the exact path of the program
		- but what if you wanted to be able to run the program from anywhere? You can do this
		by storing the program in one of the directories listed in the <envar>PATH</envar>
		environment variable. Whenever you run any program, the system looks for that program
		in each of the directories listed in the <envar>PATH</envar> environment variable and
		then runs that program. We can make this program available everywhere by simply
		copying this source file to one of the directories listed in <envar>PATH</envar>.
		
		</para>
		<screen>
		<![CDATA[
$ echo $PATH
/opt/mono/bin:/usr/local/bin:/usr/bin:/bin:/usr/X11R6/bin:/home/swaroop/bin
$ cp helloworld.py /home/swaroop/bin/helloworld
$ helloworld
Hello World
		]]>
		</screen>
		<para>
		
		We can display the <envar>PATH</envar> variable using the <command>echo</command>
		command and prefixing the variable name by <literal>$</literal> to indicate to the
		shell that we need the value of this variable. We see that
		<filename>/home/swaroop/bin</filename> is one of the directories in the PATH variable
		where <emphasis role="bold">swaroop</emphasis> is the username I am using in my
		system. There will usually be a similar directory for your username on your system.
		Alternatively, you can add a directory of your choice to the <envar>PATH</envar>
		variable - this can be done by running
		<command>PATH=$PATH:/home/swaroop/mydir</command> where
		<literal>'/home/swaroop/mydir'</literal> is the directory I want to add to the
		<envar>PATH</envar> variable.
		
		</para>
		<para>
		
		This method is very useful if you want to write useful scripts that you want to run
		the program anytime, anywhere. It is like creating your own commands just like
		<command>cd</command> or any other commands that you use in the Linux terminal or
		DOS prompt.
		
		</para>
		<caution>
			<para>
			
			W.r.t. Python, a program or a script or software all mean the same thing.
			
			</para>
		</caution>
	</section>
	<section id="getting-help">
		<title>Getting Help</title>
		<para>
		
		If you need quick information about any function or statement in Python, then you can
		use the built-in <literal>help</literal> functionality. This is very useful especially
		when using the interpreter prompt. For example, run <literal>help(str)</literal> - this
		displays the help for the <literal>str</literal> class which is used to store all
		text (strings) that you use in your program. Classes will be explained in detail in
		the chapter on object-oriented programming. <!-- FIXME : Put a link, linkend here -->
		
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
			
			Press <keycap>q</keycap> to exit the help.
			
			</para>
		</note>
		<para>
		
		Similarly, you can obtain information about almost anything in Python. Use
		<literal>help()</literal> to learn more about using <literal>help</literal> itself!
		
		</para>
		<para>
		
		In case you need to get help for operators like <literal>print</literal>, then you need
		to set the <envar>PYTHONDOCS</envar> environment variable appropriately. This can be
		done easily on Linux/Unix using the <command>env</command> command.
		
		</para>
		<screen>
		<![CDATA[
$ env PYTHONDOCS=/usr/share/doc/python-docs-2.3.4/html/ python
Python 2.3.4 (#1, Oct 26 2004, 16:42:40)
[GCC 3.4.2 20041017 (Red Hat 3.4.2-6.fc3)] on linux2
Type "help", "copyright", "credits" or "license" for more information.
>>> help('print')
		]]>
		</screen>
		<para>
		
		You will notice that I have used quotes to specify <literal>'print'</literal> so that
		Python can understand that I want to fetch help about 'print' and I am not asking it
		to print something.
		
		</para>
		<para>
		
		Note that the location I have used is the location in Fedora Core 3 Linux - it may be
		different for different distributions and versions.
		<!-- NOTE: Update this section when using newer versions of Python or Fedora -->
		
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="first-steps-summary">
		<title>Summary</title>
		<para>
		
		You should now be able to write, save and run Python programs at ease. Now that you
		are a Python user, let's learn some more Python concepts.
		
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
